<abstracts-retrieval-response xmlns="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/svapi/abstract/dtd" xmlns:dn="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/svapi/abstract/dtd" xmlns:ait="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/ani/ait" xmlns:ce="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/ani/common" xmlns:cto="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/cto/dtd" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:prism="http://prismstandard.org/namespaces/basic/2.0/" xmlns:xocs="http://www.elsevier.com/xml/xocs/dtd" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><coredata><prism:url>https://api.elsevier.com/content/abstract/scopus_id/0242489084</prism:url><dc:identifier>SCOPUS_ID:0242489084</dc:identifier><eid>2-s2.0-0242489084</eid><dc:title>Multipass Algorithm for Detection of Transient ST Segment Changes in Electrocardiogram Večprehodni algoritem za odkrivanje prehodnih sprememb segmenta ST elektrokardiograma</dc:title><prism:aggregationType>Journal</prism:aggregationType><srctype>j</srctype><subtype>ar</subtype><subtypeDescription>Article</subtypeDescription><citedby-count>1</citedby-count><prism:publicationName>Elektrotehniski Vestnik/Electrotechnical Review</prism:publicationName><source-id>16651</source-id><prism:issn>00135852</prism:issn><prism:volume>65</prism:volume><prism:issueIdentifier>5</prism:issueIdentifier><prism:startingPage>289</prism:startingPage><prism:endingPage>295</prism:endingPage><prism:pageRange>289-295</prism:pageRange><prism:coverDate>1998-12-01</prism:coverDate><openaccess/><openaccessFlag/><dc:creator><author seq="1" auid="6603254309"><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Smrdel A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Smrdel</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Aleš</ce:given-name><preferred-name><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Smrdel A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Smrdel</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Aleš</ce:given-name></preferred-name><author-url>https://api.elsevier.com/content/author/author_id/6603254309</author-url><affiliation id="60031106" href="https://api.elsevier.com/content/affiliation/affiliation_id/60031106"/></author></dc:creator><dc:description><abstract xmlns="" original="y" xml:lang="eng"><ce:para>Ischemia is a condition which can lead to insufficient oxygen supply to the heart muscle. Ischemia is transient in nature; it can be asymptomatic (silent), i.e. detectable only through changing potentials in an electrocardiogram (ECG), or symptomatic, which usually manifests as an attack of angina pectoris (chest pain). Ischemic events must be detected as soon as possible since they may lead to heart infarct. An appropriate method is the analysis of long ambulatory ECG records taken over 24 hours. The huge amount of data thus generated dictates the development of reliable automatic algorithms for the detection of significant (&gt; 100 μV) transient episodes in the ST segment compatible with ischemia (ischemic ST episodes). The fact that significant ST segment changes often appear due to non-ischemic reasons causes difficulties in detecting true ischemic episodes. The most problematic of these non-ischemic ST episodes are changes connected with the shifts of the electrical axis of heart and slow drift of the ST segment level. In this paper we describe the architecture, development and evaluation of an algorithm for automatic detection of transient ischemie and non-ischemic ST segment episodes in ambulatory records. We used the ST-T database (European Society of Cardiology ST-T Database, ESC DB) [1] containing ninety two-lead 2-hour records to develop the algorithm, and for evaluation and prediction of its "real world" performance we used our own ST database of eleven two-lead 24-hour ambulatory records. The algorithm is based on the Karhunen-Loève transform (KLT) [8] and includes a multipass adaptive technique for identifying trajectories of the QRS complex and ST segment feature vectors (see Figure 1). We expect the algorithm to be more efficient if the decision thresholds are adjusted to the record with regard to the presence or absence of intervals with extreme ST changes and with regard to the modality of the distribution of the ST segment feature-vector time series. Higher decision thresholds enable avoiding the ripples of the ST segment feature-vector time series in the intervals which contain extreme ST episodes and avoiding non-signilicant (&lt;100μV) non-ischemic episodes in the intervals which expose multimodal nature of the distribution of the feature-vector time series. The passes of the algorithm follow the preprocessing and learning phase. In the preprocessing phase, the baseline correction [2] and the exclusion of abnormal beats (as detected by the ARISTOTLE arrhythmia detector [9]) and their neighbours are performed. In the short learning phase [2], average beat is composed of 50 normal beats taken at the beginning of the record. In the first pass, the calculation of the Karhunen-Loève (KL) coefficients and feature vectors of the QRS complex and ST segment for each heart beat is performed, and noisy beats are eliminated in the KL space [4]. In the second pass, the algorithm corrects the reference ST segment zero level [5] due to its slow drift. The correction is performed by exponentially weighted updating of the values of the mean ST feature vector, s̄(k), (equation (1)), of "normal" ST segment feature vectors. In the third pass, the algorithm calculates the distribution of corrected ST segment distance function, C<inf>s</inf>(k), (equation (2)), and assesses the modality of its distribution [10]. The modality of the corrected distribution is determined by a procedure which searches for extrema and local minima of the distribution (see Figure 2). At least one extremum, E<inf>1</inf>, is always present. Its location is determined by the first sample which satisfies condition (3). The procedure detects both adjacent local minima, Min<inf>L</inf> and Min<inf>R</inf>, by searching through distribution backward and forward starting at point E<inf>1</inf>, until the difference in amplitude between two neighbouring samples does not change the sign. Each subsequent extremum, E<inf>n</inf>, is determined by amplitude of a sample Max<inf>n</inf> which satisfies condition (4). If the distribution contains one single extremum, it is considered to be unimodal, otherwise multimodal. In the fourth pass, the algorithm detects episodes in the C<inf>s</inf>(k) using an adaptive detection technique. The algorithm sequentially classifies the samples of the function as normal and deviating ones. In developing the algorithm, we followed the time and amplitude criteria [1] for the identification of ST segment episodes as were defined and used in the development of the ST-T and ST databases. We closely followed the time criteria, while the lower decision threshold L(k) (equivalent to a threshold of 50 μV which defines the beginning and end of the episode) and the upper decision threshold (equivalent to a threshold of 100 μV beyond which the ST deviation in the original signal has to be for the time longer than 30 seconds) are adaptive. The adaptive decision thresholds are based on an heuristic descriptor of trend, in our case the average exponentially weighted mean value of the corrected ST segment distance function, C<sup>A</sup><inf>s</inf>(k), (equations (5,6,7)), which estimates the nonstationary behaviour of C<inf>s</inf>(k). The decision thresholds are set at L(k) = C̄<sup>A</sup><inf>s</inf>(k) and U(k) = 2C̄<sup>A</sup><inf>s</inf>(k). The thresholds are adaptive only within a predetermined intermediate zone. The intermediate zone is bounded by a lower limit, λ<inf>l</inf>, and an upper limit, λ<inf>u</inf>, which is also adaptive. The value of the upper limit λ<inf>u</inf>(k) is dependent on a heuristic rule, which takes into consideration the trend (equation (5)) and instantaneous distance function C<inf>s</inf>(k), and switches between the values <inf>λul</inf> and λ<inf>u()</inf> (equation (8)). In the fifth pass, the algorithm detects significant axis-shifts of the heart by searching for step changes inline QRS complex and ST segment distance functions of the first order [5]. The algorithm classifies each detected ST episode as non-ischemic if the axis-shift is present within an interval of 2.5 minutes surrounding the beginning or end of the ST episode and if the ST segment deviation in original signals during the episode does not exceed 300 μV in any lead [5], Figure 3 shows examples of detecting ST episodes in the ST database. Table 1 presents the performances of the KLT algorithm to detect ST episodes with the use of the ST-T database as was achieved during its development. The aggregate gross and average sensitivity of detecting ischemic ST episodes, IE Se, and aggregate gross and average positive predictivity of detecting ischemic ST episodes, IE + P, (metrics defined in [5,11,12]) were between 81% and 88%. The obtained performances are comparable with the performances of other systems for ST episode detection developed (and evaluated) on the ST-T database. These range from 77% to 88% [2,3,4,7]. Table 2 summarizes the obtained performances of the KLT algorithm with the use of the test ST database. The aggregate gross and average IE Se were approximately 60%, the aggregate gross and average IE + P were 73% and 74% respectively. We also introduced the use of the "bootstrap" statistical method [13] to predict performance of the algorithm in the real world. Figure 4 presents distributions of expected real world performances. None of the systems in [2,3,4,7] was tested in the sense of predicting real world performance using the "bootstrap" technique on a set of records of length of 24-hours. The next generation of ST analysers will have to be able to distinguish between ischemic and non-ischemic ST episodes. Development of improved algorithms will require development of the database including 24-hour ambulatory records and a much larger number of ischemic and especially non-ischemic ST episodes. It is our opinion that in spite of the use of advanced and exhaustive methods, as well as a larger database, it will be difficult to achieve higher performance in fully automated algorithms. Tiny ischemic episodes are often surrounded or superimposed by changes in the ST segment level due to noise. Retrospective semi-automated interactive techniques represent promising new approaches to the analysis and detection of ST segment changes.</ce:para></abstract></dc:description><link href="https://api.elsevier.com/content/abstract/scopus_id/0242489084" rel="self"/><link href="https://www.scopus.com/inward/record.uri?partnerID=HzOxMe3b&amp;scp=0242489084&amp;origin=inward" rel="scopus"/><link href="https://www.scopus.com/inward/citedby.uri?partnerID=HzOxMe3b&amp;scp=0242489084&amp;origin=inward" rel="scopus-citedby"/></coredata><affiliation id="60031106" href="https://api.elsevier.com/content/affiliation/affiliation_id/60031106"><affilname>University of Ljubljana</affilname><affiliation-city>Ljubljana</affiliation-city><affiliation-country>Slovenia</affiliation-country></affiliation><authors><author seq="1" auid="6603254309"><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Smrdel A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Smrdel</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Aleš</ce:given-name><preferred-name><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Smrdel A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Smrdel</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Aleš</ce:given-name></preferred-name><author-url>https://api.elsevier.com/content/author/author_id/6603254309</author-url><affiliation id="60031106" href="https://api.elsevier.com/content/affiliation/affiliation_id/60031106"/></author><author seq="2" auid="35616708300"><ce:initials>F.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Jager F.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Jager</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Franc</ce:given-name><preferred-name><ce:initials>F.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Jager F.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Jager</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Franc</ce:given-name></preferred-name><author-url>https://api.elsevier.com/content/author/author_id/35616708300</author-url><affiliation id="60031106" href="https://api.elsevier.com/content/affiliation/affiliation_id/60031106"/></author></authors><language xml:lang="slv"/><authkeywords><author-keyword>Ambulatory monitoring</author-keyword><author-keyword>Karhunen-Loève transform</author-keyword><author-keyword>Performance evaluation</author-keyword><author-keyword>Transient ischemia detectors</author-keyword></authkeywords><idxterms/><subject-areas><subject-area code="2208" abbrev="ENGI">Electrical and Electronic Engineering</subject-area></subject-areas><item xmlns=""><ait:process-info><ait:date-delivered year="2019" month="06" day="13" timestamp="2019-06-13T13:35:31.000031-04:00"/><ait:date-sort year="1998" month="12" day="01"/><ait:status type="core" state="update" stage="S300"/></ait:process-info><bibrecord><item-info><copyright type="Elsevier">Copyright 2004 Elsevier Science B.V., Amsterdam. All rights reserved.</copyright><itemidlist><itemid idtype="PUI">128441823</itemid><itemid idtype="SNCPX">2002325775</itemid><itemid idtype="CPX">2004057872506</itemid><itemid idtype="SCP">0242489084</itemid><itemid idtype="SGR">0242489084</itemid></itemidlist><history><date-created year="2003" month="10" day="06"/></history><dbcollection>SNCPX</dbcollection><dbcollection>CPX</dbcollection><dbcollection>Scopusbase</dbcollection></item-info><head><citation-info><citation-type code="ar"/><citation-language xml:lang="slv" language="Slovenian"/><abstract-language xml:lang="eng" language="English"/><abstract-language xml:lang="slv" language="Slovenian"/><author-keywords><author-keyword xml:lang="eng">Ambulatory monitoring</author-keyword><author-keyword xml:lang="eng">Karhunen-Loève transform</author-keyword><author-keyword xml:lang="eng">Performance evaluation</author-keyword><author-keyword xml:lang="eng">Transient ischemia detectors</author-keyword></author-keywords></citation-info><citation-title><titletext xml:lang="eng" original="n" language="English">Multipass Algorithm for Detection of Transient ST Segment Changes in Electrocardiogram</titletext><titletext xml:lang="slv" original="y" language="Slovenian">Večprehodni algoritem za odkrivanje prehodnih sprememb segmenta ST elektrokardiograma</titletext></citation-title><author-group><author auid="6603254309" seq="1"><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Smrdel A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Smrdel</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Aleš</ce:given-name><preferred-name><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Smrdel A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Smrdel</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Aleš</ce:given-name></preferred-name></author><author auid="35616708300" seq="2"><ce:initials>F.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Jager F.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Jager</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Franc</ce:given-name><preferred-name><ce:initials>F.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Jager F.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Jager</ce:surname><ce:given-name>Franc</ce:given-name></preferred-name></author><affiliation afid="60031106" dptid="104580817" country="svn"><organization>Univerza v Ljubljani</organization><organization>Fak. za Racunalnistvo in Informatiko</organization><address-part>Tržaška 25</address-part><city-group>1000 Ljubljana</city-group><affiliation-id afid="60031106" dptid="104580817"/><country>Slovenia</country></affiliation></author-group><correspondence><person><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Smrdel A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Smrdel</ce:surname></person><affiliation country="svn"><organization>Univerza v Ljubljani</organization><organization>Fak. za Racunalnistvo in Informatiko</organization><address-part>Tržaška 25</address-part><city-group>1000 Ljubljana</city-group><country>Slovenia</country></affiliation></correspondence><abstracts><abstract original="y" xml:lang="eng"><ce:para>Ischemia is a condition which can lead to insufficient oxygen supply to the heart muscle. Ischemia is transient in nature; it can be asymptomatic (silent), i.e. detectable only through changing potentials in an electrocardiogram (ECG), or symptomatic, which usually manifests as an attack of angina pectoris (chest pain). Ischemic events must be detected as soon as possible since they may lead to heart infarct. An appropriate method is the analysis of long ambulatory ECG records taken over 24 hours. The huge amount of data thus generated dictates the development of reliable automatic algorithms for the detection of significant (&gt; 100 μV) transient episodes in the ST segment compatible with ischemia (ischemic ST episodes). The fact that significant ST segment changes often appear due to non-ischemic reasons causes difficulties in detecting true ischemic episodes. The most problematic of these non-ischemic ST episodes are changes connected with the shifts of the electrical axis of heart and slow drift of the ST segment level. In this paper we describe the architecture, development and evaluation of an algorithm for automatic detection of transient ischemie and non-ischemic ST segment episodes in ambulatory records. We used the ST-T database (European Society of Cardiology ST-T Database, ESC DB) [1] containing ninety two-lead 2-hour records to develop the algorithm, and for evaluation and prediction of its "real world" performance we used our own ST database of eleven two-lead 24-hour ambulatory records. The algorithm is based on the Karhunen-Loève transform (KLT) [8] and includes a multipass adaptive technique for identifying trajectories of the QRS complex and ST segment feature vectors (see Figure 1). We expect the algorithm to be more efficient if the decision thresholds are adjusted to the record with regard to the presence or absence of intervals with extreme ST changes and with regard to the modality of the distribution of the ST segment feature-vector time series. Higher decision thresholds enable avoiding the ripples of the ST segment feature-vector time series in the intervals which contain extreme ST episodes and avoiding non-signilicant (&lt;100μV) non-ischemic episodes in the intervals which expose multimodal nature of the distribution of the feature-vector time series. The passes of the algorithm follow the preprocessing and learning phase. In the preprocessing phase, the baseline correction [2] and the exclusion of abnormal beats (as detected by the ARISTOTLE arrhythmia detector [9]) and their neighbours are performed. In the short learning phase [2], average beat is composed of 50 normal beats taken at the beginning of the record. In the first pass, the calculation of the Karhunen-Loève (KL) coefficients and feature vectors of the QRS complex and ST segment for each heart beat is performed, and noisy beats are eliminated in the KL space [4]. In the second pass, the algorithm corrects the reference ST segment zero level [5] due to its slow drift. The correction is performed by exponentially weighted updating of the values of the mean ST feature vector, s̄(k), (equation (1)), of "normal" ST segment feature vectors. In the third pass, the algorithm calculates the distribution of corrected ST segment distance function, C<inf>s</inf>(k), (equation (2)), and assesses the modality of its distribution [10]. The modality of the corrected distribution is determined by a procedure which searches for extrema and local minima of the distribution (see Figure 2). At least one extremum, E<inf>1</inf>, is always present. Its location is determined by the first sample which satisfies condition (3). The procedure detects both adjacent local minima, Min<inf>L</inf> and Min<inf>R</inf>, by searching through distribution backward and forward starting at point E<inf>1</inf>, until the difference in amplitude between two neighbouring samples does not change the sign. Each subsequent extremum, E<inf>n</inf>, is determined by amplitude of a sample Max<inf>n</inf> which satisfies condition (4). If the distribution contains one single extremum, it is considered to be unimodal, otherwise multimodal. In the fourth pass, the algorithm detects episodes in the C<inf>s</inf>(k) using an adaptive detection technique. The algorithm sequentially classifies the samples of the function as normal and deviating ones. In developing the algorithm, we followed the time and amplitude criteria [1] for the identification of ST segment episodes as were defined and used in the development of the ST-T and ST databases. We closely followed the time criteria, while the lower decision threshold L(k) (equivalent to a threshold of 50 μV which defines the beginning and end of the episode) and the upper decision threshold (equivalent to a threshold of 100 μV beyond which the ST deviation in the original signal has to be for the time longer than 30 seconds) are adaptive. The adaptive decision thresholds are based on an heuristic descriptor of trend, in our case the average exponentially weighted mean value of the corrected ST segment distance function, C<sup>A</sup><inf>s</inf>(k), (equations (5,6,7)), which estimates the nonstationary behaviour of C<inf>s</inf>(k). The decision thresholds are set at L(k) = C̄<sup>A</sup><inf>s</inf>(k) and U(k) = 2C̄<sup>A</sup><inf>s</inf>(k). The thresholds are adaptive only within a predetermined intermediate zone. The intermediate zone is bounded by a lower limit, λ<inf>l</inf>, and an upper limit, λ<inf>u</inf>, which is also adaptive. The value of the upper limit λ<inf>u</inf>(k) is dependent on a heuristic rule, which takes into consideration the trend (equation (5)) and instantaneous distance function C<inf>s</inf>(k), and switches between the values <inf>λul</inf> and λ<inf>u()</inf> (equation (8)). In the fifth pass, the algorithm detects significant axis-shifts of the heart by searching for step changes inline QRS complex and ST segment distance functions of the first order [5]. The algorithm classifies each detected ST episode as non-ischemic if the axis-shift is present within an interval of 2.5 minutes surrounding the beginning or end of the ST episode and if the ST segment deviation in original signals during the episode does not exceed 300 μV in any lead [5], Figure 3 shows examples of detecting ST episodes in the ST database. Table 1 presents the performances of the KLT algorithm to detect ST episodes with the use of the ST-T database as was achieved during its development. The aggregate gross and average sensitivity of detecting ischemic ST episodes, IE Se, and aggregate gross and average positive predictivity of detecting ischemic ST episodes, IE + P, (metrics defined in [5,11,12]) were between 81% and 88%. The obtained performances are comparable with the performances of other systems for ST episode detection developed (and evaluated) on the ST-T database. These range from 77% to 88% [2,3,4,7]. Table 2 summarizes the obtained performances of the KLT algorithm with the use of the test ST database. The aggregate gross and average IE Se were approximately 60%, the aggregate gross and average IE + P were 73% and 74% respectively. We also introduced the use of the "bootstrap" statistical method [13] to predict performance of the algorithm in the real world. Figure 4 presents distributions of expected real world performances. None of the systems in [2,3,4,7] was tested in the sense of predicting real world performance using the "bootstrap" technique on a set of records of length of 24-hours. The next generation of ST analysers will have to be able to distinguish between ischemic and non-ischemic ST episodes. Development of improved algorithms will require development of the database including 24-hour ambulatory records and a much larger number of ischemic and especially non-ischemic ST episodes. It is our opinion that in spite of the use of advanced and exhaustive methods, as well as a larger database, it will be difficult to achieve higher performance in fully automated algorithms. Tiny ischemic episodes are often surrounded or superimposed by changes in the ST segment level due to noise. Retrospective semi-automated interactive techniques represent promising new approaches to the analysis and detection of ST segment changes.</ce:para></abstract></abstracts><source srcid="16651" type="j" country="svn"><sourcetitle>Elektrotehniski Vestnik/Electrotechnical Review</sourcetitle><sourcetitle-abbrev>Elektroteh Vestn Electrotech Rev</sourcetitle-abbrev><issn>00135852</issn><codencode>ELVEA</codencode><volisspag><voliss volume="65" issue="5"/><pagerange first="289" last="295"/></volisspag><publicationyear first="1998"/><publicationdate><year>1998</year><date-text xfab-added="true">1998</date-text></publicationdate></source><enhancement><classificationgroup><classifications type="SUBJECT"><classification>Engineering and Technology</classification></classifications><classifications type="ASJC"><classification>2208</classification></classifications><classifications type="SUBJABBR"><classification>ENGI</classification></classifications></classificationgroup></enhancement></head><tail><bibliography refcount="13"><reference id="5914583"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>The European ST-T database, Standard for evaluating systems for the analysis of ST-T changes in ambulatory electrocardiography</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0026705255</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Taddei A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Taddei</ce:surname></author><author seq="2"><ce:initials>G.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Distante G.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Distante</ce:surname></author><author seq="3"><ce:initials>M.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Emdin M.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Emdin</ce:surname></author><author seq="4"><ce:initials>P.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Pisani P.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Pisani</ce:surname></author><author seq="5"><ce:initials>G.B.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Moody G.B.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Moody</ce:surname></author><author seq="6"><ce:initials>C.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Zeelenberg C.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Zeelenberg</ce:surname></author><author seq="7"><ce:initials>C.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Marchesi C.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Marchesi</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>European Heart Journal</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1992"/><ref-volisspag><voliss volume="13"/><pagerange first="1164" last="1172"/></ref-volisspag></ref-info><ref-fulltext>A. Taddei, G. Distante, M. Emdin, P. Pisani, G. B. Moody, C. Zeelenberg, C. Marchesi, The European ST-T database, Standard for evaluating systems for the analysis of ST-T changes in ambulatory electrocardiography, European Heart Journal, 13, pp. 1164-1172, 1992.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914584"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>Analysis of transient ST segment changes during ambulatory ECG monitoring</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0026622286</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>F.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Jager F.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Jager</ce:surname></author><author seq="2"><ce:initials>R.G.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Mark R.G.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Mark</ce:surname></author><author seq="3"><ce:initials>G.B.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Moody G.B.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Moody</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Proc. Computers in Cardiology</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1991"/><ref-volisspag><voliss volume="91"/><pagerange first="453" last="456"/></ref-volisspag><ref-text>September</ref-text></ref-info><ref-fulltext>F. Jager, R. G. Mark, G. B. Moody, Analysis of transient ST segment changes during ambulatory ECG monitoring, Proc. Computers in Cardiology 91, pp. 453-456, September 1991.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914585"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>A system for the detection of ischemic episodes in ambulatory ECG</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0029536445</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Taddei A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Taddei</ce:surname></author><author seq="2"><ce:initials>G.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Costantino G.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Costantino</ce:surname></author><author seq="3"><ce:initials>R.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Silipo R.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Silipo</ce:surname></author><author seq="4"><ce:initials>M.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Emdin M.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Emdin</ce:surname></author><author seq="5"><ce:initials>C.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Marchesi C.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Marchesi</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Proc. Computers in Cardiology</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1995"/><ref-volisspag><voliss volume="95"/><pagerange first="705" last="708"/></ref-volisspag><ref-text>September</ref-text></ref-info><ref-fulltext>A. Taddei, G. Costantino, R. Silipo, M. Emdin, C. Marchesi, A system for the detection of ischemic episodes in ambulatory ECG, Proc. Computers in Cardiology 95, pp. 705-708. September 1995.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914586"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>Analysis of transient ST segment changes during ambulatory ECG monitorine using the Karhunen-Loève transform</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">85052236746</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>F.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Jager F.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Jager</ce:surname></author><author seq="2"><ce:initials>R.G.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Mark R.G.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Mark</ce:surname></author><author seq="3"><ce:initials>G.B.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Moody G.B.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Moody</ce:surname></author><author seq="4"><ce:initials>S.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Divjak S.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Divjak</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Proc. Computers in Cardiology</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1992"/><ref-volisspag><voliss volume="92"/><pagerange first="691" last="694"/></ref-volisspag><ref-text>September</ref-text></ref-info><ref-fulltext>F. Jager, R. G. Mark, G. B. Moody, S. Divjak. Analysis of transient ST segment changes during ambulatory ECG monitorine using the Karhunen-Loève transform. Proc. Computers in Cardiology 92, pp. 691-694, September 1992.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914587"><ref-info><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0347530913</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>F.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Jager F.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Jager</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-publicationyear first="1994"/><ref-text>Ph. D. Thesis, Automated detection of transient ST-segment changes during ambulatory ECG-monitoring, Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za elektrotehniko in računalništvo</ref-text></ref-info><ref-fulltext>F. Jager, Ph. D. Thesis, Automated detection of transient ST-segment changes during ambulatory ECG-monitoring, Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za elektrotehniko in računalništvo, 1994.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914588"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>Model-based estimation of cardiovascular features</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0345179452</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>P.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Laguna P.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Laguna</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Proc. Analysis of Non-invasive Cardiovascular Signals in Ischemic Heart Disease: Methods, Development and Evaluation</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1996"/><ref-volisspag><pagerange first="20"/></ref-volisspag></ref-info><ref-fulltext>P. Laguna, Model-based estimation of cardiovascular features. Proc. Analysis of Non-invasive Cardiovascular Signals in Ischemic Heart Disease: Methods, Development and Evaluation, pp. 20, 1996.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914589"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>Continuous monitoring and detection of ST-T changes in ischemic patients</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0242405675</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>R.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Silipo R.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Silipo</ce:surname></author><author seq="2"><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Taddei A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Taddei</ce:surname></author><author seq="3"><ce:initials>C.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Marchesi C.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Marchesi</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Proc. Computers in Cardiology</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1994"/><ref-volisspag><voliss volume="94"/><pagerange first="225" last="228"/></ref-volisspag><ref-text>September</ref-text></ref-info><ref-fulltext>R. Silipo, A. Taddei, C. Marchesi, Continuous monitoring and detection of ST-T changes in ischemic patients, Proc. Computers in Cardiology 94, pp. 225-228, September 1994.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914590"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>A New Approach to Feature Selection Based on the Karhunen-Loève Expansion</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0015755579</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>J.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Kittler J.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Kittler</ce:surname></author><author seq="2"><ce:initials>P.C.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Young P.C.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Young</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Pattern Recognition</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1973"/><ref-volisspag><voliss volume="5"/><pagerange first="335" last="352"/></ref-volisspag></ref-info><ref-fulltext>J. Kittler, P. C. Young, A New Approach to Feature Selection Based on the Karhunen-Loève Expansion, Pattern Recognition, 5, pp. 335-352, 1973.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914591"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>Development and evaluation of a 2-lead ECG analysis program</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0020948396</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>G.B.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Moody G.B.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Moody</ce:surname></author><author seq="2"><ce:initials>R.G.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Mark R.G.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Mark</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Proc. Computers in Cardiology</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1982"/><ref-volisspag><voliss volume="82"/><pagerange first="39" last="44"/></ref-volisspag><ref-text>September</ref-text></ref-info><ref-fulltext>G. B. Moody, R. G. Mark, Development and evaluation of a 2-lead ECG analysis program, Proc. Computers in Cardiology 82, pp. 39-44, September 1982.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914592"><ref-info><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0348160516</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Smrdel A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Smrdel</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Diplomska Naloga. Razvoj Večprehodnega Algoritma za Odkrivanje Prehodnili Epizod Segmenta ST Elektrokardiograma</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1997"/><ref-text>Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za računalništvo in informatiko</ref-text></ref-info><ref-fulltext>A. Smrdel, Diplomska naloga. Razvoj večprehodnega algoritma za odkrivanje prehodnili epizod segmenta ST elektrokardiograma, Univerza v Ljubljani, Fakulteta za računalništvo in informatiko, 1997.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914593"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>Performance measures for algorithms to detect transient ischémie ST segment changes</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0026634381</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>F.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Jager F.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Jager</ce:surname></author><author seq="2"><ce:initials>G.B.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Moody G.B.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Moody</ce:surname></author><author seq="3"><ce:initials>A.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Taddei A.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Taddei</ce:surname></author><author seq="4"><ce:initials>R.G.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Mark R.G.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Mark</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Proc. Computers in Cardiology</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1991"/><ref-volisspag><voliss volume="91"/><pagerange first="369" last="372"/></ref-volisspag><ref-text>September</ref-text></ref-info><ref-fulltext>F. Jager, G. B. Moody, A. Taddei, R. G. Mark, Performance measures for algorithms to detect transient ischémie ST segment changes, Proc. Computers in Cardiology 91, pp. 369-372, September 1991.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914594"><ref-info><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0346269745</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-text>American National Standard Institute, Ambulatory electrocardiographs, ANSI/AAMI EC38-1994, American National Standard Institute, Inc., Association for the Advancement of Medical Instrumentation</ref-text></ref-info><ref-fulltext>American National Standard Institute, Ambulatory electrocardiographs, ANSI/AAMI EC38-1994, American National Standard Institute, Inc., Association for the Advancement of Medical Instrumentation.</ref-fulltext></reference><reference id="5914595"><ref-info><ref-title><ref-titletext>Use of the "boot-strap" to assess the robustness of the performance statistics of the arrhythmia detector</ref-titletext></ref-title><refd-itemidlist><itemid idtype="SGR">0345611463</itemid></refd-itemidlist><ref-authors><author seq="1"><ce:initials>P.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Albrecht P.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Albrecht</ce:surname></author><author seq="2"><ce:initials>G.B.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Moody G.B.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Moody</ce:surname></author><author seq="3"><ce:initials>R.G.</ce:initials><ce:indexed-name>Mark R.G.</ce:indexed-name><ce:surname>Mark</ce:surname></author></ref-authors><ref-sourcetitle>Journal of Ambulatory Monitoring</ref-sourcetitle><ref-publicationyear first="1988"/><ref-volisspag><voliss volume="1" issue="2"/><pagerange first="171" last="176"/></ref-volisspag></ref-info><ref-fulltext>P. Albrecht, G. B. Moody, R. G. Mark, Use of the "boot-strap" to assess the robustness of the performance statistics of the arrhythmia detector, Journal of Ambulatory Monitoring, 1(2), pp. 171-176, 1988.</ref-fulltext></reference></bibliography></tail></bibrecord></item></abstracts-retrieval-response>